A 1993 paper in the Journal of Financial
Economics with nearly 15,000 citations
today changed financial economics and
portfolio management forever. Eugene
Fama and Kenneth French found that a
group of three factors explained the
vast majority of differences in returns
across diversified portfolios. These
findings had and continue to have
sweeping implications for both the study
and practice of investment management.
You guys like to make fun of me in the
comments for talking about Fama and
French all the time, which I definitely
do, and this paper is one of the reasons
they always come up. It's research that
every investor should understand whether
they choose to apply its findings or
not. Personally, this paper is the
foundation of how I think about
investing and building portfolios. I'm
Ben Felix, Chief Investment Officer at
PWL Capital, and I'm going to tell you
why common risk factors in the returns
on stocks and bonds changed everything
we thought we knew about finance and
investing.
I probably don't have to tell you that
this is going to be a nerdy video. Let's
be honest, that's probably why you're
here. I think it'll be worth it. I'm
going to cover this paper's methodology,
results, and its enduring impacts. I'll
also talk later in the video about how
this paper's findings apply to investors
today, so be sure to stick around for
that. The fundamental premise of this
paper is that multiple factors, a term
I'll get more into in a minute, affect
asset prices and expected returns, and
that these factors can help to explain
why different types of stocks and bonds,
and therefore different investment
portfolios, have different expected
returns. An expected return, as it
sounds, is the return you expect from
investing in a stock or bond. The study
of expected returns is often referred to
as asset pricing because those two
things are directly related. An asset's
price is based on its expected return,
and its expected return can be inferred
from its price. Expected returns are not
guaranteed outcomes, but as we will see,
they do contain information. This makes
sense. You would pay more for a safer
asset than a riskier one, all else
equal. It's commonly known that stocks
are riskier than bonds and therefore
have higher expected returns. But, what
if some types of stocks have
systematically higher expected returns
than others? In Fama and French's
original framing, common undiversifiable
risks that a lot of investors are
sensitive to, how to explain why some
stocks have higher returns than others.
I do want to note, that while this paper
looks at both stock and bond factors, I
will focus mostly on stocks in this
video. If a stock is exposed to more of
a certain type of risk that a lot of
investors are sensitive to, that stock
needs to have a higher expected return
to entice investors to buy it, all else
equal. The idea that investors might
care about multiple types of risk was
not new when this paper came out. Robert
Merton and others had written about this
idea before, but figuring out what those
risks might be and how to measure them
was new. To understand why this
perspective was so impactful, it's
important to understand what came before
it. In 1964 and 1965, researchers
developed the capital asset pricing
model, or CAPM. This model connected a
stock's expected return to how its price
moves relative to the overall market,
expressed as its market beta, or
commonly just beta. A beta of one means
that a stock tends to move up and down
by a similar amount to the market. A
higher beta, more than one, means that
the stock will tend to be up more when
the market is up and down more when the
market is down, and vice versa for a
beta less than one. According to this
single factor model, where exposure to
market risk is the only risk care about,
stocks with higher betas should on
average deliver higher returns. The CAPM
was a big deal in finance. I mean, big
enough to win Bill Sharpe the Nobel
Memorial Prize in Economic Sciences in
1990 for his work on it, because it
formalized a relationship between risk
and expected return. And it did a pretty
good job of explaining the observed
returns of stocks. Even though the CAPM
defined and then dominated the study of
asset pricing from its inception through
the 70s and 80s, research had
consistently come out showing that
certain types of stocks had higher
returns than what could be explained by
their CAPM betas. Since these
observations could not be explained by
an asset pricing model, by the asset
pricing model at the time, they were
referred to as anomalies. An asset
pricing anomaly could mean one of two
things. If we believe the CAPM is a
perfect model for explaining expected
returns, anomalies must mean that
markets are not efficient. Or, if we
know that markets are efficient, the
CAPM must be wrong. The asset pricing
model must be wrong. This point turns
out to be impossible to resolve. It's
actually called the joint hypothesis
problem. We can't say whether markets
are efficient without having an asset
pricing model to test market efficiency,
and we can't prove whether an asset
pricing model is right without knowing
whether markets are efficient. Anyway,
this initial asset pricing research was
important and it's where Fama and French
started in their 1993 paper. They focus
on three key problems with the CAPM.
One, small stocks earned higher average
returns than large stocks, unexplained
by differences in their CAPM betas. Two,
high book-to-market or value stocks
earned higher average returns than low
book-to-market or growth stocks. Again,
unexplained by differences in their CAPM
betas. And three, the relationship
between beta and average returns was
weaker than CAPM predicted, with low
beta stocks earning higher returns than
the model suggested. Basically, CAPM
claimed that two companies with the same
betas should have similar expected
returns regardless of their size or
value characteristics, or I mean, any
other characteristics for that matter.
Anything not following the model was
considered a mispricing or an asset
pricing anomaly, and Fama and French
wanted to explain the known anomalies at
the time. In this paper, Fama and French
noted these patterns that small stocks
and value stocks tended to perform
better on average than CAPM would
predict, stating right at the top of the
paper that the cross-section of average
returns on US common stocks shows little
relation to the market betas of the
sharp litner asset pricing model. That's
blunt language for an academic paper and
was followed up with the suggestion that
maybe the standard model, the CAPM, was
ignoring risk factors that are in fact
priced by the market. It is on this
basis that Fama and French built their
now famous three-factor asset pricing
model. Rather than just looking at the
market factor, Fama and French developed
a three-factor model that relates a
stock's expected return to the market
factor, a size factor, and a relative
price or value factor. The market factor
is the same concept from the CAPM, how
much the stock or portfolio moves when
the overall market moves. This factor
shows whether stocks went up or down
with the market. This pricing factor
remains important because broad market
movements still affect most stocks
regardless of their size or value
characteristics. The size factor is
pretty straightforward. It's based on
the size of companies. More
specifically, this factor is denoted as
SMB or small minus big. It refers to the
difference in returns between small
company stocks and large company stocks.
If small stocks outperform large stocks
in a given period, the SMB premium was
positive in that period. If large stocks
do better, the premium was negative. By
including this factor in the model, the
model captures whether being a small
company is related to systematic return
variation that investors are compensated
for. Then there's the value factor,
denoted as HML or high minus low. This
is referring to book-to-market valuation
ratios. Book-to-market is basically the
company's accounting value compared to
its stock market value. High
book-to-market stocks are value stocks.
They're cheaper in market price relative
to the book value of their assets. Low
book-to-market stocks are growth stocks.
Investors are paying more for future
potential, pushing prices further above
their book values or accounting values.
HML measures the difference in returns
between value stocks and growth stocks.
Again, high minus low. When value stocks
outperform the HML premium or value
premium is positive and vice versa. This
factor captures the effects of any
return premium that investors receive
for holding value stocks rather than
growth stocks, which again, that was one
of the anomalies at the time.
Each of these factors is what's called a
long short portfolio. SMB, for example,
is long small cap stocks and short big
stocks. The specific constructions of
the factor portfolios have some details
that are even too nerdy, I think, for
this video, but the main idea is that
they're capturing return variations
related to company size and relative
price, which had been well documented as
return anomalies back when this paper
was written. Okay, before we get into
the next part of their methodology and
the main results, which are where things
get really interesting and practically
useful, make sure to subscribe to this
channel if you haven't already. I break
down nerdy investing topics like this to
help you make more informed decisions
with your finances. Okay, let's keep
going on the finance paper that changed
everything. Take their new asset pricing
model for a test drive, Fama and French
formed diversified portfolios by sorting
stocks based on size and value
characteristics. They split stocks into
five size groups and five book-to-market
groups, creating 25 total portfolios to
test. This method allowed them to
capture every combination of these
factors, small value stocks, big growth
stocks, and everything in between.
They show that these various groups of
stocks have significant variation in
average returns, and then they test
whether their three-factor asset pricing
model is able to explain that variation.
This is where Fama and French did
something pretty groundbreaking at the
time that still shows up in tons of
academic finance papers and practical
investment analysis today. They used it
time series regressions to test how well
their asset pricing factors explain the
returns of their test portfolios. A time
series regression looks at the returns
of a portfolio over time and asks how
much of the variation in returns is
explained by the asset pricing factors
being used. Running a time series
regression is pretty straightforward
with the tools available to investors
today. You can do it in Excel or using
free online tools like Portfolio
Visualizer. The output of a time series
regression includes factor loadings or
coefficients, which tell you how your
portfolio moves relative to each factor,
and an alpha, which is the portion of
returns that is not explained by the
asset pricing model. That last term,
alpha, is really important. It was first
used to describe excess risk-adjusted
returns in a 1968 academic paper,
another banger if you're into this kind
of thing. That paper used the single
factor capital asset pricing model to
ask whether actively managed mutual fund
managers were generating returns in
excess of what should be expected based
on the amount of risk they were taking.
It's worth mentioning that active
managers in the study were not able to
beat the market, but that's another
topic. And remember, that model only
accounted for market risk. In the
context of Fama and French's 1993 paper,
they took each of the 25 test portfolios
and tracked their performance from July
1963 to December 1991, and then used
their model to try to explain the
differences in their returns. For each
portfolio, the regression estimated how
its returns co-moved with the three
factors in the model, and whether there
were any large alphas, excess returns
unexplained by the model. They also
measured the R-squared values of the
regressions. R-squared measures the
explanatory power of a regression. What
percentage of a portfolio's ups and
downs over time can be attributed to the
factors in the model. An R-squared of
one or 100% would mean perfect
explanatory power, and zero would mean
the factors explained nothing.
What Fama and French found in terms of
alphas and R-squared values across the
25 test portfolios was pretty
incredible. They found that three-factor
regressions on these portfolio
constructions resulted in R-squared
values ranging from 0.83 to 0.97,
about 0.93 on average. In fact, 21 of
the 25 portfolios tested had R-squared
values over 0.9. That That that this
model explains around 90% of the
differences in returns of diversified
stock portfolios. This test also
provided two other key data points.
First, every test portfolio combination
has a beta value close to one. This
consistency reinforces the fact that
variation in returns is explained by
more than just exposure to market beta
since the market beta exposures were
nearly the same in every case, and yet
returns varied widely. That would be
surprising if market beta fully priced
all assets, but it followed the pattern
that Fama and French had predicted. In
their tests, Fama and French found that
market beta could only explain around
60% of the differences in returns across
their test portfolios. Let that sink in
for a minute. We went from being able to
explain about 60% of the differences in
returns between diversified portfolios
with the CAPM to being able to explain
around 90% with the Fama and French
three-factor model. Another important
observation was that these three-factor
regressions resulted in near zero
intercepts or alphas on almost all test
portfolios. The one exception was
small-cap growth stocks, which had much
lower returns than the three-factor
model could explain, leaving lots of
room for future research, which I'll
talk about in a minute. The finding of
minimal alphas is important and might be
one of the most compelling validations
of the model. They demonstrate that once
you account for market, size, and value
exposures, there are basically no
persistent unexplained returns remaining
in most of their portfolio sorts. Other
than the 25 test portfolios formed on
size and price to book, Fama and French
also tested portfolios formed on
dividends to price and earnings to
price, two other characteristics that
had been associated with higher returns.
They again found that their three-factor
model explained the returns of these
portfolios very well, shattering the
beliefs of dividend-focused investors
everywhere. With their analysis, Fama
and French showed that size and value
don't need to be viewed as mysterious
asset pricing anomalies or market
inefficiencies. Rather, they can be
viewed as systematic risk factors that,
together with market beta, almost fully
account for return differences across
diversified portfolios. It's worth
mentioning that it's debatable whether
the factors in the model are risk
factors or artifacts of persistent
mispricing. That's one of those things
that's really hard to test in a way that
offers definitive proof one way or
another. All right, I don't mean to sit
here and nerd out about time series
regressions. Oh, okay, fine. That's
exactly what I mean to do. But this
asset pricing model and series of tests
really did change the way we viewed
markets. Our ability to explain
differences in returns between different
types of diversified portfolios went
from pretty good to in some cases near
perfect. Remember, CAPM using just
market beta typically explained only
somewhere between 60 and maybe 80% of
differences in returns between
diversified portfolios. By adding size
and value, Fama and French jumped to
over 90% explanatory power with their
three-factor model. What this showed is
that a three-factor model could capture
fundamental systematic drivers of
returns that CAPM had completely missed.
The other area that this research
touches is traditional active
management. Remember the 1968 paper
showing that active managers don't
typically outperform after adjusting for
market risk? Well, with more factors in
the model, the data on traditional
active management only got worse. Fama
and French looked at that in later
research using their three-factor model.
Basically, if an active fund has beaten
the market, there's a really good chance
it did so by maintaining exposure to
some of the well-known factors. This
matters because if that is all an active
manager is doing, you could probably
replicate their factor exposure at a
lower cost than the fee that most active
managers charge. Altogether, the
findings in this paper challenged and
built on the single-factor CAPM asset
pricing to create a much more
comprehensive framework for how
investors should think about building
and evaluating investment portfolios
systematically. After this paper, the
study of empirical asset pricing, that
is looking at asset returns and figuring
out which factors may be driving them,
took off. Researchers wanted to find the
best factors and create better asset
pricing models. It became a bit of a
problem or a joke. In 2011, John
Cochrane in his presidential address to
the American Finance Association
described the proliferation of factors
as a zoo, a factors zoo. You could
probably even call it a factor slop to
use the language from my recent video on
ETF slop. A 2016 census from Zoo, Lu,
and Harvey confirmed this concept
finding that 316 distinct factors had
been published in academic journals at
that time and more since then. This
created a whole new set of techniques
for choosing factors and comparing asset
pricing models.
In the face of the slop proliferation,
Fama and French went on to update their
groundbreaking 1993 research in 2015,
which introduced two new asset pricing
factors, profitability and investment.
Profitability is expressed as RMW or
robust minus weak. That's the excess
return expected from companies with high
profitability over those with weak
profitability. Investment is expressed
as conservative minus aggressive.
Companies that grow their assets slowly,
conservative, tend to outperform those
that pour cash into rapid asset growth,
aggressive. The addition of these two
new factors created the Fama and French
five-factor model. The five-factor model
did help to solve some problems that the
three-factor model couldn't and it
further improved the explanatory power
of the model closer to explaining 95% of
the differences in returns between
diversified portfolios. It's now what I
would call the workhorse asset pricing
model in academic finance. Don't get me
wrong, there is still plenty of ongoing
debate both in academia and in practice
about which factors make sense and which
asset pricing model we should be using.
I'm pretty comfortable saying that when
transaction costs are accounted for,
Fama and French's five-factor model is a
very strong foundation for thinking
about portfolio construction and
evaluating portfolio performance. Okay,
I told you I would bring this back to
practical relevance. There are fund
companies that using this research, this
asset pricing research to build real
investment portfolios, real investment
products that you can invest in. They're
kind of like low-cost index funds that
deliver exposure to more than just
market risk, but they're not actually
index funds in most cases. Dimensional
Fund Advisors has a long history of
implementing factor investing research.
Eugene Fama, one of this paper's
authors, was a founding director and
remains on the board today. Kenneth
French, the other co-author, has
long-standing connections to
Dimensional. As I detailed in a previous
video, their track record using these
strategies has been very good over
decades. One catch is that Dimensional
used to be only available through
financial advisors, though at least in
the US, they're now available as ETFs
that anybody can buy. Not in Canada,
though, unfortunately. More recently,
Avantis Investors, a Dimensional
competitor, launched similar products
and they have just launched ETFs in
Canada through CIBC. If you want details
on that, we did just release a podcast
episode with the Avantis CIO. I'll do a
deeper dive on these products in another
video. Full disclosure, real quick, my
firm uses Dimensional Fund Advisors
funds pretty extensively. We are not
paid by Dimensional or Avantis, and I
was not being paid to mention them in
this video. What does this all mean for
you? Evidence suggests that long-term
expected returns are driven by exposure
to specific factors, factors that we
know about due to decades of academic
research, implying that investors may
achieve higher expected returns by
tilting toward certain types of stocks.
But which types of stocks and knowing
how to do it effectively and at a low
cost is a whole other question.
Fortunately, there are fund companies
like Dimensional Fund Advisors and
Avantis Investors that do this, creating
low-cost and broadly diversified
investment portfolios specifically built
to take academic theory and apply it to
your portfolio. Like I said at the
beginning, this seminal paper forms the
foundation for a big part of how I think
about investing. It's also part of the
reason that my firm, PWL Capital, has
been using Dimensional Fund Advisors
products since we helped bring them to
Canada back in 2003.
If you want to learn more about PWL and
how we apply this thinking to our
clients' portfolios, you can click right
here. Or if you want to nerd out on one
of the most controversial papers in
finance, you can click here.